Guide to the Dissent Magazine Records TAM 642
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dissent Magazine Records
1952-2013
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
TAM 642
9 Linear Feet 9 record cartons
Dissent is a quarterly magazine that provides political commentary from intellectuals on the political left. This collection is largely comprised of Dissent's editorial board and administrative records, which contain documentation of editorial decisions from the 1950s to the early 2000s, including correspondence among editorial board members and minutes from board meetings. The collection also contains the personal papers of Emanuel Geltman, who was one of Dissent's founding members. Other materials in this collection include indices of Dissent issues in the 1990s, pamphlets, and scrapbooks documenting the development of the magazine, photographs, and audio visual recordings of special events.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials donated by Sarah Leonard on behalf of Dissent Magazine in 2014. The accession number associated with this gift is 2014.004.
Appraisal
Three boxes containing subscription materials, permissions, and other documents containing sensitive personal information have been separated from this collection.
Correspondence and materials related to the donation of Henry M. Patcher's papers to SUNY Albany, which includes a copy of the deed of gift were also separated from this collection for confidentiality reasons.
Microfilmed copies of Dissent, 1990-2010 were removed from this collection due to existing duplicate issues in Tamiment's collections.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into series by subject and creator.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dissent is a quarterly magazine of political and social criticism. Founded in 1954 by Irving Howe, Emanuel Geltman, and Stanley Plastrik, Dissent has published articles critiquing the political ideologies of the left and right for over 60 years. Informed by democratic socialist ideology and intellectuals on the political left, Dissent's founders positioned the magazine in contrast to the liberalism of the West and communism of the East. Although Dissent identifies itself with the democratic socialism of its founders, its editors and contributors represent a broad spectrum of political outlooks. Since its formation it has published articles by a number of prominent intellectuals including Hannah Arendt, Norman Mailer, Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, Ellen Willis, Richard Wright, George Packer, as well as many others.
Irving Howe served as Dissent's first editor from 1954 until his death in 1993. Following Howe's death, Mitchell Cohen and Michael Walzer served as co-editors of the magazine until 2013. The current editor of Dissent magazine is historian Michael Kazin.
Custodial History
The Emanuel Geltman Papers were donated to the Foundation for the Study of Independent Social Ideas/Dissent in 2008. These materials were donated to the Tamiment Library in 2014 as part of Dissent's records.
The archived website was migrated from the California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service to the Internet Archive's Archive-It Service in November 2015. The link to California Digital Library was removed in October 2017.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of Dissent magazine, a quarterly publication that offers political and social commentary from intellectuals on the political left. A large portion of Dissent's records relate to editorial board decisions and administrative procedures. The collections also contains several indices of Dissent issues in the 1990s, pamphlets, and scrapbooks documenting the development of the magazine.
The collection's editorial board records contain correspondence and meeting minutes from the 1950s to the early 2000s, as well as materials relating to the formation of the magazine's non-profit organization the Foundation for the Study of Independent Social Ideas (FSISI) in 1980. It also contains several records relating to the founding of Dissent in 1954, including the magazines' original business license and documentation of their first bank account. Administrative files largely relate to the day-to-day activities of the magazine, including the creation of Dissent's website and archive. Several files relating to the creation of the Dissent archive contain correspondence documenting the magazine's attempt to compile documentation related to founding member and longtime editor Irving Howe. Several of these files contain photocopies of Howe's correspondence with Dissent writers.
This collection also contains a series of papers from Dissent editorial board member Emanuel Geltman. These papers largely relate to Geltman's political activity prior to his involvement with Dissent.
Other materials contained in this collection include video recordings of conferences and lectures and promotional materials related to special events.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to technical or privacy issues, archived websites may not be exact copies of the original website at the time of the web crawl. Certain file types will not be captured dependent on how they are embedded in the site. Other parts of websites that the crawler has difficulty capturing includes Javascript, streaming content, database-driven content, and highly interactive content. Full-Text searches of archived websites are available at https://archive-it.org/organizations/567.
Journalism -- United States.; Cohen, Mitchell; Dissent (New York, N.Y.); Emanuel, Geltman, 1914-1995; Foundation for the Study of Independent Socal Ideas, Inc. (New York); Walzer, Michael; Howe, Irving.; Kazin, Michael; Leonard, Sarah; Dissent Magazine
- Editorial Board Records (Box 1, Box 2)
  Scope and Content Note
  This series contains the files of the Dissent editorial board. Correspondence and board meeting minutes make up the majority of this series. This series also contains several documents related to the formation of Dissent between 1952-1953 as well as materials related to the magazine's non-profit organization the Foundation for the Study of Independent Social Ideas, which was formed in 1980. Other materials contained in this series include materials related to conferences and special issues.
- Administrative Files (Box 3, Box 5)
  This series consists of Dissent's administrative files which contain correspondence, subject files, promotional and fundraising materials, materials related to the creation of magazine's website, and documents and correspondence related to the Dissent archive. Subject files and correspondence are arranged alphabetically, while other files are grouped by subject. Files relating to the Dissent archive contain correspondence related to the formation of the archive and efforts to compile correspondence from founding member and longtime editor Irving Howe. Several a number of these materials contain photocopies of Howe's correspondence with Dissent contributors.
- Emanuel Geltman Papers, 1949-1985 (Box 7)
  This series contains materials and writings from Emanuel Geltman, who was a member of Dissent's editorial board for many years. The majority of Geltman's materials relate to his political involvement in socialism in the 1930s and 1940s, prior to the formation of Dissent, while a small number of materials relate to the 1970s and 80s.
- Indices, 1990s (Box 4)
- Pamphlets, 1978-1995 (Box 4)
  This series contains copies of Democracy Journal from 1981 to 1983, as well as a number of assorted pamphlets from the late 1970s to 1990s.
- Special Events and Memorabilia, 1954-2013 (Box 6)
  This series contains several scrapbooks documenting Dissent magazine's development from 1954-1989 and other assorted memorabilia related to special events such as parties and anniversaries.
- Photographs, circa 1970s-2002; 4 folders (Box 6)
  This series contains assorted photographs of Irving Howe and Michael Walzer. It also contains several photographs from a panel discussion on media bias from 2002.
- Electronic Records, 1990-2010
- Multimedia, 1989-2002
  Contians recordings of special events, conferences and interviews 1990s-2000
  - Videorecordings (Box 8)
  - Cassette tapes (Box 8)
- Archived Website, May 5, 2012-ongoing
  Dissent Magazine, founded in 1954 by Irving Howe, is a quarterly leftist/social democratic intellectual magazine of politics and culture edited by Michael Kazin and Michael Walzer. Dissent's website contains direct links to articles from current issues and back issues, a blog, online articles, videos, and topical issues.